export default  Social_Study_Ministry_2015 = [
  {
    id: "h1",
    Number_of_Questions: "60 Questions",
    Time_Allowed: "1 hour"
  },
  {
    id: 'h2',
    header1: " Addis Ababa CITY ADMINISTRATION EDUCATION BUREAU GRADE EIGHT Ministry EXAM Social Study 2015/JANNUARY 9-2024"},
  {
    id: "I",
    header1: "I. READ THE FOLLOWING QUESTIONS CAREFULLY AND CHOOSE THE CORRECT ALTERNATIVE ANSWER FOR THE FOLLOWING QUESTIONS",
     },
    {
    id: 1,
    question: "Which one of the following process results in the formation of rift valley?",
    options: ["Folding", "Faulting", "Earthquakes", "Volcanism"],
    correct_option: " Faulting ",
explanation: "Rift valleys and block/Horst/ mountains are major features formed by faulting."
  },
  {
    id: 2,
    question: "One of the following feature is created by wind action:",
    options: ["Exfoliation", "Stalagmite", "Sheet Erosion", "Sand Dune"],
    correct_option: "Sand Dune",
explanation:" Sand dune is a small hill of sand formed by the action of the wind"
  },
  {
    id: 3,
    question: "Which one of the following is caused by running water?",
    options: ["Soil Erosion", "Destruction of Cities","Release of Dangerous gases","Breaking of Rocks into Pieces"],
    correct_option: "Soil Erosion ",
explanation:" Erosion is the movement of broken rock and soil particles from one place to another by running water, wind, moving ice or sea waves."
  },
  {
    id: 4,
    question: " Which one of the following describes the stratosphere?",
    options: ["It Contains Three-Fourth of the Atmospheric Mass", " It is the Coldest Part of the Atmosphere",     " It is the Layer of Extreme low Air Density", " It is the Layer Where Ultraviolet Ray is Absorbed"],
    correct_option: "It is the Layer Where Ultraviolet Ray is Absorbed ",
explanation:" The ozone layer is found in the stratosphere. It is a layer of gas which absorbs much of the sun‟s ultraviolet radiation,"

  },
  {
    id: 5,
    question: " What distinguishes weather from climate is that:",
    options: ["Climate is the Average Weather Condition of a Place Over Long Period of Time", " Weather is the Atmospheric Condition of a Place for Period of Time", " Climate Indicates Daily Changes in Rainfall and Temperature", " Weather Indicates What the Physical Environment of a Place Looks Like"],
    correct_option: "Weather is the Atmospheric Condition of a Place for Period of Time ",
explanation:" Weather is the condition of the atmosphere over a short period of time. Weather includes daily changes in precipitation, air pressure, temperature, wind, etc."

  },
  
  {
    id: 6,
    question: " What is the effect of Latitude on Temperature?",
    options: ["The Equator Gets Low Intense Insolation", "Polar Areas Get Low Intensity Insolation", ' In Spring Equinox, the Overhead is at the Equator', ' December 21 Represents North Summer'],
    correct_option: " Polar Areas Get Low Intensity Insolation ",
explanation:" At the equator, the overhead sun is high and high intensity insolation is received. At the poles, the sun’s rays are slanting (oblique), so the amount of insolation is low"
  },
  {
    id: 7,
    question: " If the maximum and minimum temperature of a place are 35°C and 15°C, respectively what is the range of temperature?",
    options: ["50°C", "20°C ", "15°C ", "35°C "],
    correct_option: "20°C ",
explanation:" The range of temperature is the difference between the maximum and minimum temperatures. In this case, the maximum temperature is 35°C and the minimum temperature is 15°C, so the range is 35°C - 15°C = 20°C."
  },
  {
    id: 8,
    question: "Which language belongs to the Cushitic language family? ",
    options: ["Guragigna ", "Basketto ", "Afarigna ", "Gumuz "],
    correct_option: " Afarigna ",
explanation:" Cushitic languages are mostly spoken in central, southern and eastern Ethiopia (mainly in Afar, Oromia and Somali regions). Example: Afarigna, Agewigna, Afan Oromo, Sidamigna, Somaligna"

  },
  {
    id: 9,
    question: "Manufacturing industries are grouped as? ",
    options: ["Tertiary Economic Activity ", "Secondary Economic Activity ", "Primary Economic Activity", " Quaternary Economic Activity "],
    correct_option: " Secondary Economic Activity ",
explanation:" Secondary economic activities pertain to adding value to already existing products by changing their form via processing, etc. It includes manufacturing, construction and power production."

  },
  {
    id: 10,
    question: " 1n which economic activity most of the people in Developed Countries are engaged? ",
    options: ["Manufacturing ", " Forestry ", " Mining ", " Agriculture "],
    correct_option: " Manufacturing",
explanation:" The developed countries have a large share of the manufacturing industries. Whereas; in developing countries, the great majority of people still work in the agriculture sector"

  },
  {
    id: 11,
    question: " Which economic activity contributes the largest share of their national output in developing countries? ",
    options: ["Manufacturing ", " Agriculture ", " Fishery ", " Forestry "],
    correct_option: " Agriculture ",
explanation:"Please Refer Question  #10"

  },
  {
    id: 12,
    question: " Which trade activity involves the selling of goods directly to consumers? ",
    options: ["Export Trade ", " Import Trade", " Wholesale Trade ", " Retail Trade "],
    correct_option: " Retail Trade ",
explanation:" Retail trade is an action of selling goods directly to consumers by retailers."

  },
  {
    id: 13,
    question: " Which one of the following dominates Ethiopia's export items? ",
    options: [' Forest Products ', ' Manufacturing Products ', ' Mineral Products ', ' Agricultural Products '],
    correct_option: "Agricultural Products ",
explanation:" Ethiopia’s export trade is dominated by agricultural products. At present, the major export products of Ethiopia include coffee, livestock products (leather, live animals and meat), oil seeds and pulses, fruits, vegetables and flowers, textiles, natural gum, spices and mineral products."

  },
{
    id: 14,
    question: " Which trade activity is carried out between two different countries? ",
    options: ['Domestic Trade ', 'Internal Trade ', 'International Trade ', ' Retail Trade '],
    correct_option: " International Trade ",
explanation:" External trade- is also known as international trade. As the term denotes this trade occurs between two different countries."

  },
    {
    id: 15,
    question: " Which economic sector contributes much to the export trade of most developing countries? ",
    options: ["Manufacturing ", " Fishery ", " Mining ", " Agriculture "],
    correct_option: "Agriculture",
explanation: "Please Refer Question  #10"

  },
    {
    id: 16,
    question: " What do we call the amount of a good that buyers are willing and able to purchase? ",
    options: ["Supply ", " Surplus ", " Demand ", " Stock "],
    correct_option: " Demand ",
explanation:" Demand is the amount of a good that buyers are willing and able to purchase. Supply is the amount of a good that sellers are willing and able to sell."

  },
  {
    id: 17,
    question: " When we supply and demand of a product is the same, the market condition created is called? ",
    options: ["Equilibrium Price"," Excess Demand"," Excess Supply",
"Surplus Production "],
    correct_option: " Equilibrium Price ",
explanation:" The point where the supply and demand curves intersect is called market equilibrium"

  },
  {
    id: 18,
    question: " A market situation with uniform price and the same goods being offered is called? ",
    options: ["Moderately Competitive ", " Perfect Competition ", " High Competition "," Imperfect Competition "],
    correct_option: "Perfect competition ",
explanation: " In Perfect competition emarket \n" +
"	Each buyer knows that there are several sellers from which to choose. \n" +
"	Sellers know that each buyer purchases only a small amount of the total amount sold. \n" +
"	The goods being offered for sale are exactly the same, so they have uniform price. \n" +
"	The buyers and sellers are so numerous that no single buyer or seller has any influence over the market price. \n" +
"	Buyers and sellers are free to enter or leave the market at any time they like."
  },
  {
    id: 19,
    question: " Which one of the following minimizes supply problem for consumers? ",
    options: ["Hoarding of Products to Create Shortage ", " Black Marketing of Products ", " High Price for Products ", " Sufficient supply of Products "],
    correct_option: "Sufficient supply of Products",
explanation:""

  },
  {
    id: 20,
    question: " Which one of the following is the benefit of wild animals? ",
    options: ["Illegal Hunting ", " Soil Conservation ",
     " Tourism Industry ", " Forest Conservation "],
    correct_option: " Tourism Industry ",
    explanation:" Wildlife is important to balance ecosystem, provide food, tourism, source of medicine, recreational purposes and for the development of the economy."

  },
  {
    id: 21,
    question: " Which one of following factor affects the proper utilization of soil resources? ",
    options: ["Poor Farming Methods ", " Improved Farming Methods "," Skilled Farmers "," Use of Advanced Technology "],
    correct_option: "Poor Farming Methods",
explanation:" methods in the conservation of soil includes: \n" +
"	Terracing \n" +
"	Afforestation \n" +
"	Crop Rotation \n" + 
"	Reforestation \n" +
"	Shelter belts \n" +
"	Check Dams \n" +
"	Strip cropping and \n" +
"	Contour ploughing" 
  },
   {
    id: 22,
    question: " Which one of the following is unwise utilization of natural resources? ",
    options: ["Wildlife Protection "," Water Pollution "," Forest Conservation "," Soil Conservation "],
    correct_option: " Water Pollution ",
explanation:" "
},
{
    id: 23,
    question: " Which one of the following is a method of water conservation? ",
    options: ["Deforestation "," Modern Irrigation Methods "," Crop Rotation "," Illegal Hunting "],
    correct_option: " Modern Irrigation Methods ",
explanation:" The following methods are useful to conserve water:- \n" +
"  -	Protection of water from pollution \n" +
"  -	Rational use of groundwater \n" +
"  -	Renovation of traditional water harvesting methods \n" +
"  -	Use of modern irrigation methods: \n" +
"  -	Increasing forest cover \n" +
"  -	Conserving water in industries \n" +
"  -	Water conservation by municipal bodies"
},
{
    id: 24,
    question: " Which one of the following is a method of wildlife conservation? ",
    options: ["Burning of Forest "," Overgrazing "," Illegal Hunting "," Establishing Parks"],
    correct_option: " Establishing Parks ",
explanation:" Measures of wildlife conservation includes \n" +
"  -	Educate the people \n" +
"  -	Laws should be made to punish persons who are killing of wild animals. \n" +
"  -	Establishing National parks, game reserves and sanctuaries. \n" +
"  -	Conservation of endangered species of wild animals."
},
{
    id: 25,
    question: " The planting of two or more crops in the same field for soil conservation is called? ",
    options: ["Afforestation "," Crop Rotation "," Strip Cropping "," Terracing "],
    correct_option: " Strip Cropping ",
explanation:" Strip cropping: involves the planting of two or more crops in the same field. The crops may differ in height, time of harvest and use of nutrients."
},
{
  id: 26,
  question: " Which of the following countries contribute the highest volume of water to the Nile River?",
  options: ["Ethiopia"," Sudan ","Egypt"," Tanzania "],
  correct_option: " Ethiopia ",
explanation:""
},
{
  id: 27,
  question: " Who first sailor who landed to India from Portugal? ",
  options: ["Christopher Columbus "," Ferdinand Magellan "," Vasco Da Gama "," Amerigo Vespucci "],
  correct_option: " Vasco Da Gama ",
explanation:" Vasco da Gama sailed round the continent as far as East Africa. In East Africa he found an Arab sailor who showed him the way to India across the Indian Ocean"
},
{
  id: 28,
  question: " Which one was the achievement of Renaissance in Science? ",
  options: ["Shakespeare's Playwright of Romeo and Juliet "," Johann Gutenberg Printing Machine "," Leonardo da Vinci's Paints of the Last Supper "," Galileo Galilei's Improvement of the Telescope "],
  correct_option: " Galileo Galilei's Improvement of the Telescope ",
explanation:" Galileo Galilei (1564-1642) an Italian astronomer and physicist, propounded the law of falling bodies and greatly improved the telescope"
},
{
  id: 29,
  question: " What was the cause of reformation against the Roman Catholic Church? ",
  options: ["Church's Abuse of Nepotism and Sale of Indulgences "," Establishment of Monastery by the Church "," The Way the Pop is Appointed "," Protestant Movement "],
  correct_option: "Church's Abuse of Nepotism and Sale of Indulgences",
explanation:" The Church’s abuses of worldliness, Nepotism, Simony, and Sale of indulgences were the cause of reformation against the Roman Catholic Church"
},
{
  id: 30,
  question: " Which one describes the First Industrial Revolution(1750-1879)? ",
  options: ["Use of Electricity and Petroleum as Source of Power "," Use of Steam and Coal as Source of Energy "," Invention of Newer and Faster Means of Transportation "," Mankind has Entered the Space Age "],
  correct_option: "Use of Steam and Coal as Source of Energy",
explanation:" first phase of the Industrial Revolution consisted of invention of the first complex machines ,the building of the first factories, the development of steam as a source of power, the expansion of the output of basic materials-coal, iron and steel and the introduction of new methods of transportation and communication."
},
{
  id:31,
  question: " What was the Basic Cause for World War Il? ",
  options: ["The Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand "," German Invasion of France "," Nationalism Feeling "," Treaty of Versailles "],
  correct_option: "Nationalism Feeling",
explanation:" Totalitarianism, Militarism, Nationalism and Imperialism were the Basic Cause for World War Il"
},
{
  id:32,
  question: " Which countries formed the Triple Alliance during World War l? ",
  options: ["Germany, Italy and Japan "," America, Russia and Britain "," Britain, France and Russia "," Germany, Italy and Austria-Hungary "],
  correct_option: " Germany, Italy and Austria-Hungary ",
explanation:" The Triple Alliance (later renamed Central powers) linked Germany with Austria-Hungary and Italy. It was signed in 1882."
},
{
  id: 33,
  question: " What consequence of World War Il? ",
  options: ["The United States and Russia Emerged as the Major World Power "," German, Britain and France Emerged as the Major World Power ",
  " The Formation of the League of Nation to KeepPeace and Security "," Germany, Italy and Japan Won the War after Defeating Britain and France "],
  correct_option: "The United States and Russia Emerged as the Major World Power",
explanation:" Consequences of the World War II were: \n" +
"  -	The war was the most costly in history and most destructive in history \n" +
"  -	Germany, Italy and Japan totalitarian systems were overthrown. \n" +
"  -	The United States and Russia emerged as the major world powers. \n" +
"  -	Great Britain and France declined as world powers"  
},
{
  id:34,
  question: " Which country belongs to the Socialist block after World War Il? ",
  options: ["The United Nation of America "," Britain "," The Soviet Union "," West Germany"],
  correct_option: " The Soviet Union ",
explanation:" The Allied Powers were Britain, France and Russia. In June 1941, the Soviet Union joined the Allies after Germany attacked it"
},
{
  id:35,
  question: " Which countries were the first actors of slave trade in Africa? ",
  options: ["Commercial Elites of Africa "," Portuguese and Spain "," Britain and France "," Caribbean Countries "],
  correct_option: " Portuguese and Spain ",
explanation:" At first, the Portuguese and the Spanish were the main organizers of the trade "
},
{
  id:36,
  question: " In 	triangular slave trade route what do the European ships carry from Europe to Africa? ",
  options: ["Cotton Cloths and Metal Hardware "," Sugar Cane , Tobacco and Cotton "," Slaves from Europe "," Coffee and Sugar Cane "],
  correct_option: " Cotton Cloths and Metal Hardware ",
explanation:" The principal European imports to Africa were cheap manufactured goods-mainly glass, cotton cloth, metal hardware and cheap and substandard guns"
},
{
  id:37,
  question: " Which country was colonized by Italy? ",
  options: ["Ethiopia "," South Africa "," Libya "," Cameroon "],
  correct_option: " Libya ",
explanation:" By 1914 Italy controlled Eritrea, Italian Somaliland, and Libya. In 1936 Italy attempted to colonize Ethiopia but it was defeated at the battle of Adwa."
},
{
  id: 38,
  question: " What was the consequence of colonization upon Africans? ",
  options: ["Upgraded African Culture "," Drained Wealth from the Colonies "," Established Manufacturing Industries "," Educate the Colonial People "],
  correct_option: " Drained Wealth from the Colonies ",
explanation:" Colonialist nations drained wealth from the colonies, discouraging colonial manufacturing, exploited the native workers by requiring long hours for little pay, expected an attitude of racial and cultural superiority, discriminated against the colonial peoples and degraded their native cultures."
},
{
  id:39,
  question: " What reason for the non-violent independence of West African countries? ",
  options: ["Britain was the Colonizer "," Portuguese Gave their independence "," French doesn't Want to Fight with Africans "," Absence of White Settlers "],
  correct_option: "Absence of White Settlers",
explanation:" Non-violent: in different African states independence was achieved fairly smoothly. The main reason for this was that these African states had no white settlers. For example, by 1960 all West African French colonies were achieved full independence."
},
{
 id:40,
  question: " How many countries founded the Organization of African Union? ",
  options: ["By 32 African States "," By 54 African States"," By 53 African States "," By 55 African States "],
  correct_option: " By 32 African States ",
explanation:" The OAU was formed in 1963 in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, by the 32 African states that had achieved independence at the time"
},

{
  id:41,
  question: " Which African leader proposed the loose organization of African countries after independence? ",
  options: ["President Nkrumah of Ghana "," President Ahmed Ben Bella of Algeria "," Emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia "," President Samora Machel of Mozambique "],
  correct_option: "President Nkrumah of Ghana",
explanation:" President Nkrumah of Ghana argued that, single African state can be powerful enough to stand by itself economically and militarily, and he stated that Africa must unite or die. Emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia pointed that we should avoid linguistic, racial, economic, and political differences - among the African nations, and recommended a loose organization. Haile Selassie’s views overcame."
},
{
  id:42,
  question: " Which one of the following was the reason for the change of the Organization of African Unity to African Union? ",
  options: ["Support Colonized Countries to get their Independence "," Remove Apartheid from South Africa and Neighboring Countries "," Avoid the Continent from Colonization and Apartheid "," Promoting Peace, Security, Democracy and Good Governance "],
  correct_option: "avoid the continent from colonization and apartheid",
explanation:" The OAU’s main objectives were to: promote the unity and solidarity of African states; coordinate and intensify their cooperation and efforts to achieve a better life for the peoples of Africa, safeguard the sovereignty and territorial integrity of member states; avoid the continent from colonization and apartheid; promote international cooperation within the United Nations framework; and harmonize members’ political, diplomatic, economic, educational, cultural, health, welfare, scientific, technical and defense policies."
},
{
  id:43,
  question: "Which king of Ethiopia attempted to unify Ethiopia under one king but failed to do and died in 1868? ",
  options: ["Emperor Yohannes IV "," Emperor Tewodros Il "," Emperor Menilek Il "," Emperor Haileselassie I "],
  correct_option: "Emperor Tewodros II ",
explanation:" In order to realize his vision of Unified Ethiopia under one king he defeated one major regional leader after another."},
{
  id:44,
  question: " At which battle field Emperor Tewodros Il defeated Dajjach Goshu Zewude, the lord of Gojjam? ",
  options: ["Battle of Ayshal "," Battle of Gorgora Bichen "," Battle of Guramba "," Battle of Darasge "],
  correct_option: " Battle of Guramba ",
explanation:" On 27th Nov. 1852, he defeated Dajjach Goshu Zewude, the lord of Gojjam, at the Battle of Guramba. "
},
{
  id:45,
  question: " During Emperor Menilek Il regime, which resisted and fought with Menilek's army? ",
  options: ["Abba Jifar Il of Jimma, "," Kumsa Moreda of Leqa Naqamite"," Joti Tullu of Leqa Qellam "," Kawo Tona of Walayta "],
  correct_option: " Abba Jifar Il of Jimma ",
  explanation: "Abba Jifar II was the ruler of the Kingdom of Jimma from 1839 to 1889. He was a powerful and influential ruler who resisted the expansion of the Ethiopian Empire under Emperor Menelik II. In 1882, Abba Jifar II signed a treaty with Menelik II, agreeing to become a vassal of the Ethiopian Empire. However, he later broke the treaty and fought against Menelik II's forces. In 1889, Abba Jifar II was defeated by Menelik II's forces and was forced to abdicate. \n" +

"Kumsa Moreda of Leqa Naqamite, Joti Tullu of Leqa Qellam, and Kawo Tona of Walayta were all rulers of smaller kingdoms in Ethiopia who also resisted the expansion of the Ethiopian Empire under Menelik II. However, they were all defeated by Menelik II's forces and were forced to submit to his rule."
},
{
  id:46,
  question: " What was the agreement reached between Emperors Yohannes IV and Meniek Il on March 20, 1878 at Leche? ",
  options: ["Meniek Il to Pay Annual Tribute to Emperor Yohannes IV "," Yohannes IV to Pay Annual Tribute to Emperor Menilek Il "," Menilek Il Not to Expand in Any Direction "," Meneliek Il Should not Claim the  Title of King at All"],
  correct_option: " Menilek Il Not to Expand in Any Direction ",
explanation:" On March 20, 1878, Emperors Yohannes IV and Menelik II of Ethiopia met at Leche to discuss their differences. The two emperors had been at odds for some time, and the meeting was intended to resolve their disputes peacefully. \n" +

" The agreement reached at Leche was that Menelik II would not expand his territory in any direction. This meant that he would not attack Yohannes IV's territory, nor would he try to expand into the territories of other Ethiopian kingdoms. \n" +

" The agreement was a major victory for Yohannes IV, as it prevented Menelik II from becoming too powerful. It also helped to stabilize the region and prevent further conflict. \n" +

" However, the agreement was not without its problems. Menelik II was not happy about being forced to limit his expansion, and he soon began to violate the terms of the agreement. This led to renewed conflict between the two emperors, which eventually culminated in the Battle of Adwa in 1896. \n" +

" Despite its problems, the agreement reached at Leche was a significant event in Ethiopian history. It helped to prevent further conflict between the two emperors and it stabilized the region."
},
{
  id:47,
  question: " Which was the major import item in the early 19th Century? ",
  options: ["Ivory "," Civet Musk ", " Coffee "," Abujedie Cloth "],
  correct_option: " Abujedie Cloth ",
explanation:" Coffee became the principal export item and cotton sheeting known as abujedie became importing item, much valued for clothing as well as for making tents. "
},

{
  id:48,
  question: " Why the long distance trade of 19th century changed its direction from north to eastward? ",
  options: ["The Djibouti-Addis Ababa Railway ", " The Opening of the Ports of Asab "," The decline of Matamma as inland port ", " Shift of the capital to Gondar "],
  correct_option: " The Djibouti-Addis Ababa Railway ",
  explanation: "In the late 19th and early 20th century the direction of long distance trade was changed from the northern to the south and eastward. The reasons were: \n" +
"o	Shawan victory over Gojjam at the Battle of Embabo \n" +
"o	The decline of Gondar and Matamma as a result of the Ethio-Mahdist hostilities \n" +
"o	The foundation and growth of Addis Ababa as the political center of the empire \n" +
"o	The opening of the Dijibouti-AddisAbaba railway and the  \n" +
"o	Establishment of Gambella as a major outlet of Ethiopian’s next to Djibouti \n" +
"o	The decline of the ports of Massawa and Assab."
},

{
  id:49,
  question: " During the Emperor Haileselassie Ethiopia's external relation was mainly with ____",
  options: ["Soviet Union "," China ",   " United states Of America "," Arabian countries "],
  correct_option: "United states Of America ",
explanation:" The diplomatic relation between Ethiopia and USA was initiated in 1903 with the arrival of the Skinner Mission to the court of Emperor Menilek II and the conclusion of a treaty of Friendship and Commerce."
},
{
  id:50,
  question: " The cause for Egyptians conquer from 1869-1876 was ",
  options: ["Khedive Ismail interest to control the head water of the Nile "," To colonize Ethiopia and the neighboring countries ", " To control the trade route along the Red sea ",  " To control the trade route along the Gulf of Aden "],
  correct_option: " Khedive Ismail interest to control the head water of the Nile ",
explanation:" From 1869-1876, the Egyptians had long been interested in establishing control over Ethiopia. The causes were Khedive Ismail ambitious plan of empire building to control all the head waters of the Nile and to get resources to recover government financial collapse."
},
{
  id:51,
  question: " Yohannes IV was killed by the Mahdists at the battle of: ",
  options: ["Gunda "," Gura "," Matamma "," Adwa "],
  correct_option: " Matamma ",
explanation:"Refer Your text Book Page 170"
},
{
id:52,
question: " In 1869 Italy occupied for the first time the port of: ",
options: ["Massawa "," Tajura ", " Mombasa "," Assab "],
correct_option: " Assab ",
explanation:" In 1869, Italy acquired the port of Assab. The evacuation of Egyptian had also secured Zeila and Berbera for the British and Tajura for the French."
},
{
id:53,
question: " The treaty that was signed between Menilek Il and Antonelli of Italy in October 1883 was the ___",
options: ["Hewett Treaty "," Treaty of Friendship and Commerce ",
" Treaty of Wuchale "," Convention of Neutrality "],
correct_option: " Treaty of Friendship and Commerce ",
explanation:"The first treaty was signed between the Italian representative Count Pietro Antonelli and Emperor Menilekon May 21, 1883. The agreements were: Consular exchange, free movement of people, free trade and free propagation of religion."
},
{
  id: 54,
  question: " Emperor Haileeselassie left for Geneva in 1936 to appeal to ",
  options: ["The league of nation ",  " African Union "," United nation ",  " Organization of African Unity "],
  correct_option: " The league of nation ",
explanation:" Emperor Haile Selassie left for Geneva in 1936 to appeal to the League of Nations for help against the Italian invasion of Ethiopia."
},
{
  id: 55,
  question: " Which of the following is the effect of climate change? ",
  options: ["Nuclear war ",   " Acid rain "," Urbanization ",  " Drought and famine "],
  correct_option: "Drought and famine",
explanation:" Nuclear war, Acid rain and Urbanization are factors responsible for climate change"
},
{
  id: 56,
  question: " What is meant by mitigation measure in climate change? ",
  options: ["Measures That can be taken to address the impact of climate change "," Measures that can be taken to avoid the increase of pollutant emission. "," Construction of infrastructure to overcome consequnces of climate change "," Take preventive measures such as evacuation, land use change and health issues. "],
  correct_option: "Measures that can be taken to avoid the increase of pollutant emission ",
explanation:""
},
{
  id: 57,
  question: " Which one is adaptation measure to be taken to solve climate change? ",
  options: ["Practice energy efficiency ",
  " Greater use of renewable energy ",
  " Landscape restoration like reforestation ",
  " Carbon tax and emission markets "],
  correct_option: "Practice energy efficiency.",
explanation:""
},
{
  id: 58,
  question: " Which one is natural source of air pollution? ",
  options: ["Gas emissions from active volcanoes ",
  " Nuclear explosions of radioactive rays ",
  " Industrial emission of carbon dioxide ",
  " Burning of wood and charcoal "],
  correct_option: " Gas emissions from active volcanoes ",
explanation:" Natural Causes: - Gas emissions from active volcanoes, marsh gas, spores of fungi and pollens are the natural causes of air pollution."
},
{
  id: 59,
  question: " Which one is the direct cause of water shortage in agricultural activities? ",
  options: ["Human disease such as trachoma ",  " Impact on crop and livestock production ",
  " Peoples drinking of unsafe water ",  " Lack of industrial water "],
  correct_option: " Impact on crop and livestock production ",
explanation:""
},

{
  id: 60,
  question: " Which one of the following is the effect of deforestation that brings loss of animals and plants? ",
  options: ["Erosion and flooding "," Increased greenhouse gases "," Loss of habitat "," Depletion of water in the atmosphere "],
  correct_option: " Loss of habitat ",
explanation:" Deforestation is the permanent removal of trees to make room for something besides forest. \n" +
"Deforestation is the permanent removal of trees to make room for something besides forest. This can include clearing the land for agriculture or grazing, or using the timber for fuel, construction or manufacturing. \n" +
"  -	Loss of habitat: \n" +
"  -	Soil erosion \n" +
"  -	Climate change \n" +
"  -	Water pollution"
},

]

